Mohammad Elayan, MSc

PhD Student and Graduate Research/Teaching Assistant melayan2@huskers.unl.edu — 402-802-6765

Department of Civil & Environmental Engineering, University of Nebraska-Lincoln

Profile

I am a PhD student and a Graduate Research Assistant at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln. With over 9 years of experience as a transportation engineering professional in Dubai, UAE, I have contributed to more than 100 projects. My research includes various aspects of transportation engineering, and I have co-authored four publications.

Education

• PhD in Civil Engineering - Transportation Engineering

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA GPA: 4.000

2023–Present

• MSc in Civil Engineering - Transportation Engineering

Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan GPA: 91.6% (Rank: 1)

2011-2013

• BSc in Civil Engineering - Transportation Engineering

Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan

GPA: 82.3% (Rank: 16) 2006–2011

Research

Google Scholar Profile: scholar.google.com

ORCID: 0009-0001-2562-5694

Total Citations: 72

Peer-Reviewed Publications

- Al-Khateeb, G., Al-Suleiman, T., Khedaywi, T., Elayan, M. (2016). "Studying Rutting Performance of Superpave Mixtures Using Unconfined Dynamic Creep and Simple Performance Tests." Road Materials and Pavement Design, Vol. 19 (2).
- Alsheyab, M., Khedaywi, T., Elayan, M. (2013). "Laboratory Study on Solidification/ Stabilization of Unwanted Medications Using Asphalt as a Binder." *Journal of Material Cycles and Waste Management*, Vol. 15 (2).
- Al-Suleiman, T., Elayan, M. (2013). "Gap Acceptance Behavior at U-turn Median Openings Case Study in Jordan." Jordan Journal of Civil Engineering, Vol. 7 (3).

Experience

University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, NE, USA

Graduate Research Assistant Graduate Teaching Assistant January 2023–Present January 2024–Present

- Part of Dr. Jason Hawkins's research team at the Nebraska Transportation Center, focusing on transportation safety, planning, and advanced technologies for EVs and AVs.
- Teaching Assistant for Civil Engineering Analysis II and Principles of Transportation Engineering.

TrafQuest, Dubai, UAE

Senior Transportation Engineer Transportation Engineer

January 2019–January 2023 June 2013–January 2019

- ullet Managed over 100 projects, including strategic transportation studies in the UAE and MENA region.
- Key tasks included travel demand forecasting, traffic analysis, roadway network performance evaluation, transport integration, and safety analysis.

Jordan University of Science and Technology, Irbid, Jordan Research Assistant

Teaching Assistant

2011

2012 - 2013

- Conducted research on highway material performance and traffic operations optimization.
- Taught laboratory courses in Surveying, Highway Materials, and Engineering Statics.

Core Capabilities

- Traffic analysis, Transport planning, Traffic management, Transport modeling
- Crash analysis, Geometric design, Statistical analysis, Research, Machine learning
- Software: Python, R, Julia, ArcGIS, QGIS, VISSIM, Synchro, SIDRA, SPSS